Guide to the Howard Kelly Collection of Florence Nightingale Prints and Photographs, circa 1840-1949 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Howard Kelly Collection of Florence Nightingale prints and photographs circa 1840-1949 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Kelly, Howard A.
1.0 Linear Feet 60 Items
Howard Atwood Kelly was a surgeon, gynecologist, professor, author, collector of medical memorabilia, and founder of the Kensington Hospital in Philadelphia; he served as the first professor of obstetrics and gynecology at Johns Hopkins Hospital and School of Medicine. Among his interests was the life of Florence Nightingale and her memorialization through images.
The Howard Kelly Collection of Florence Nightingale Prints and Photographs represents the collecting efforts of Howard Atwood Kelly, a surgeon, professor, author, and collector of medical memorabilia. The collection comprises 60 images and other memorializations associated with Florence Nightingale, 19th century nurse and healthcare reformer. Image formats include engravings, photographs (some of which are albumens), lithographs, mezzo tints, prints, and postcards; in addition, there are photographic and slide reproductions of drawings, lithographs, engravings, crayon drawings, paintings, and sculptures. Almost all the images are mounted on cardstock boards. Portrayals of Nightingale span her adult lifetime; there are images of her during her early career as a nurse in Britain, and providing nursing care for wounded soldiers in Turkey during the Crimean War. There are also images of her birth and death places. Also included are one piece of popular sheet music (1857) and typed explanatory notes. Reproductions also accompany many of the images. Arranged in rough chronological order by date of publication or creation. Acquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Howard Kelly Collection of Florence Nightingale Prints and Photographs was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 2011 as a transfer from the Medical Center Library.
Biographical Note
Florence Nightingale was born in 1820 to a wealthy family living at the time in Florence, Italy. She was instrumental in the establishment of training for nurses, improvements in standards of hygiene, and compassionate care of patients in military and civilian hospitals and the workhouses of Britain. Her activities and service during the Crimean War, 1854-1856, elevated her to iconic status; the popular press began reporting extensively on her travels and her crusade for healthcare and sanitary reforms. She founded the Nightingale School of Nurses at St. Thomas' Hospital in London in 1860, the first of its kind. She also traveled to Greece and Egypt. During the Indian Mutiny, the American Civil War, and the Franco-Prussian War she consulted with military officials on hospitals and medical care. She wrote extensively on nursing, healthcare and sanitation, and healthcare statistics. Her life was memorialized through named institutions, biographies, photographic and print images, music, dramas, poetry, sculptures, and plaques. She died in London in 1910.
Collection Overview
The Howard Kelly Collection of Florence Nightingale Prints and Photographs represents the collecting efforts of Howard Atwood Kelly, a surgeon, gynecologist, professor, author, collector of medical memorabilia, and founder of the Kensington Hospital in Philadelphia. He served as the first professor of obstetrics and gynecology at Johns Hopkins Hospital and School of Medicine. The collection is composed of images and memorials associated with Florence Nightingale, 19th century nurse, author, and sanitation and healthcare reformer. Image formats include engravings, photographs, lithographs, mezzo tints, prints, postcards, and photographic and slide reproductions of drawings, lithographs, engravings, crayon drawings, paintings, and sculptures. Unless otherwise noted, all images are in black and white. Almost all are mounted on cardstock boards. The images depict Florence Nightingale throughout her adult life; some also portray monuments to Nightingale, and geographical locations associated with her birth, death, and nursing career, including her activities in Scutari (Istanbul) tending to wounded soldiers, the peak of her popularization in the media of the time. Also included are one piece of sheet music (1857) and typed explanatory notes. Reproductions in slide and photograph format accompany many of the images. Arranged chiefly in chronological order by date of publication or creation. Acquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Nightingale, Florence, 1820-1910
Nightingale, Florence, 1820-1910 -- Pictorial works
History of nursing -- Great Britain
Nurses -- Great Britain -- History -- 19th century
Military nursing -- Great Britain -- History -- 19th century
Crimean War, 1853-1856
Crimean War, 1853-1856 -- Hospitals -- History.
Üsükar (Istanbul, Turkey) -- Pictorial works
Albumen photographs
Black and white photographs
Engravings
Lithographs
Mezzotints
Postcards
Sheet music
Slides
History of Medicine Collections (Duke University)
Related Material
History of Medicine Print Materials Collection [contains several contemporary newspapers with stories and images of Nightingale's activities during the Crimean War]
Rubenstein Library, Duke University
Contents of Collection
- Photographs and Prints Series, circa 1840-1949, (3 boxes)
  Contains photographs, lithographs, engravings,and prints as well as photographic reproductions of drawings, engravings, crayon drawings, paintings, and sculptures memorializing Florence Nightingale. The images were created between 1840 and 1949, and most are mounted on card stock. Also includes a piece of popular sheet music published in 1857. Arranged in original order as they appear in the folders, roughly chronological. Some images are mounted together on one board.
  - Portrait of Florence Nightingale, half-length, at about 20 years old; photographic reproduction of the painting by Augustus Leopold Egg, R.A., circa 1840, (1 photograph of a painting); 10.75 x 7 inches (Box 1, Folder 1)
    The original portrait is owned by the National Portrait Gallery in London, England.
  - St. Thomas Hospital, Southwark, London, erected 1555, with a statue of the Founder-King, Edward VI, 1840, (1 engraving) 3.5 x 4.5 inches (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Portrait of Florence Nightingale, half-length, oval, from a drawing by Elizabeth Rigby (Lady Eastlake) made in July 1846, (1 photograph of a drawing, 1 slide reproduction) 14.75 x 13.5 inches (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Includes one slide reproduction of the image made in 1939.
  - The Zouaves Advancing to the Assistance of the British at the Battle of Inkermann, 1854, (engraving) 7 x 10.25 inches (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Drawn by G.W. Terry, lithograph made by G. Greatbach for the London Printing and Publishing Company.
  - Portrait of Florence Nightingale, half-length, reading a book, circa 1854, (1 engraving, 2 reproductions) 6 x 4.5 inches (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Engraved by G. E. Perine and Company, New York. Includes two reproductions of the image; one photograph of a crayon-drawing of the portrait, and one photograph reproduction of the crayon drawing of the portrait in oval.
  - Drawing of Florence Nightingale in her later years, (1 photograph of a drawing) 5 x 4 inches (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Copied from memory by Augustin Rischy from another drawing.
  - Florence Nightingale Memorial Medal of the Red Cross, undated, (1 photograph) 5 x 7 inches (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Portrait of Florence Nightingale, half-length, seated to the left, reading a book she holds in her left hand, approximately 1853-1856, (1 photograph of a steel-engraving) 7.75 x 5.5 inches (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Engraved by G. E. Perine and Company, N.Y., prob. during Crimean War.
  - Portrait of Florence Nightingale, full-length, standing with an owl, 1855, (1 stippled engraving, 2 reproductions) 14.5 x 11 inches (Box 1, Folder 2)
    The image is based on a drawing by Parthenope Nightingale, Florence Nightingale's sister. Published 6 June 1855 by Paul and Dominic Colnaghi and Company, London, England. Includes two reproductions of the image; one photographic reproduction of the image and one printed reproduction of the image on a card from the Nursing Mirror Christmas card, circa 1951.
  - Florence Nightingale and her Friends (Mr. Bracebridge and others)on Catcart's Heights, near Sebastopol, May 1855, (1 sepia-tinted lithograph, 1 slide reproduction) 13.5 x 18.5 inches (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Based on a sketch by Selina Mills, better known as Lady Bracebridge,and later drawn by Lady Verny and Lady Anne Blunt. Lithograph made by Day and Son, Lithographers to the Queen. Includes one reproduction in slide format made in 1949.
  - An Angel of Mercy, Florence Nightingale holding a lamp at a soldier's bedside at Scutari, Turkey, 1855, (1 mezzo tint engraving, 1 slide reproduction) 17.25 x 13.5 inches (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Published June 20, 1855 by Lloyd Brother and Co. Includes one reproduction in slide format made in 1948.
  - The Soldier's Friend, three-quarters-length portrait of Florence Nightingale to the left, undated, (1 stipple-engraving) 5.25 x 3.75 inches (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Engraved and published by Ellis, London.
  - 'I was sick and ye visited me.' Florence Nightingale at Therafia Hospital, 1855, (1 photogravure) 6 x 7.25 inches (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - One of the Wards of the Hospital at Scutari, 1856, (1 colored lithograph, 2 photo reproductions) 14 x 18.75 inches (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Drawn by W. Simpson, lithograph made by E. Walker for Day and Son, Lithographers to the Queen. Published 21 April 1856 by Paul and Dominic Colnaghi. Includes a two-page typed-script manuscript titled "A Ward in the Hospital at Scutari," and two black and white photographic reproductions.
  - A Mission of Mercy, Florence Nightingale at Scutari, 1856, (1 photograph) 5 x 7.75 inches (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Photograph of the original drawing by Jerry Barratt. Includes one reduction in photograph format.
  - The Battle of Inkermann, undated, (1 engraving) 7 x 10.5 inches (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Drawn by W. H. Kearney, engraved by G. Greatbach for the London Printing and Publishing Company.
  - Photograph of statue erected to Miss Nightingale in London, undated, (1 photograph) 5.25 x 4 inches (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes one reproduction in photograph format.
  - Hospital and Cemetery at Scutari, 1856, (1 colored lithograph, slide reproduction) 14 x 19.25 inches (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Drawn by W. Simpson, lithograph made by J. Needham for Day and Son, Lithographers to the Queen. Published 26 April 1856 by Paul and Dominic Colnaghi. Includes one reproduction in slide format made in 1947 and a one-page typed-script manuscript pasted onto the back of the image titled "Hospital and Cemetery at Scutari."
  - The Nightingale's Song to the Sick and Wounded, 1857, (1 piece of sheet music) 13.5 x 8.75 inches (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Lithographic title page of a 6-page piece of sheet music depicts Nightingale in a military ward. Poetry by C. A. Somerset, music by W. West, dedicated to Miss Burdett Coutts. Originally sung and arranged by Miss Pearce.
  - Portrait of Florence Nightingale, three-quarters length, circa 1858, (1 photograph) 5.75 x 4 inches (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Includes autograph note reading "About Oct. 30, i.e. 1858. See Cook's life vol. 1, p. 394."
  - Nursing in Union Hospitals, 1865, (1 engraving) 8.75 x 6.25 inches (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Commissioned by the U.S. Sanitary Commission and the U.S. Christian Commission. Entered according to Act of Congress, 1865 by W. S. Williams and Company.
  - The Duke of Cambridge Distributing the Crimean Medal to the French Troops, 1866, (1 engraving) 7 x 10.5 inches (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Engraving drawn by R. Hind, engraved by W. Hulland for the London Printing and Publishing Company.
  - Panel for Florence Nightingale memorial, Liverpool, England, 1918, (1 photograph) 8.5 x 6 inches (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Photograph of the sculpture by Charles J. Allen. Includes one reproduction in photographic format as well as 2 typescript notes pasted onto the back of the image regarding the provenance of the photograph.
  - Miss Nightingale visiting the Herbert Hospital, Woolwich, London, undated, (1 photograph) 4.5 x 6.25 inches (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Includes two reproductions; one reproduction in photograph format, and one reproduction in slide format.
  - The Right Honorable Sidney Herbert, undated, (1 photograph of an engraving) 9.25 x 7 inches (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Original engraving by Francis Grant and George Raphael Ward, London.
  - 10 South Street, Park Lane, London, undated, (1 photograph) 8 x 5.5 inches (Box 2, Folder 5)
    London residence of Florence Nightingale where she died in 1920.
  - Bradford Street, undated, (1 photograph) 6 x 8 inches (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Collection of Florence Nightingale prints and books, undated, (1 photograph) 7.5 x 9.5 inches (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Photograph shows a collection of prints and books about Florence Nightingale. Many of the images appear in this collection.
  - The Florence Nightingale Bequest to the Royal United Service Institution, London, undated, (1 photograph) 6 x 8 inches (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Florence Nightingale's Home, Embley Park, Romsey, Hampshire, undated, (1 photograph) 7.25 x 10.5 inches (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Florence Nightingale Memorial at St. Paul's Cathedral, London, undated, (1 photograph of a bas-relief sculpture) 8 x 6 inches (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Florence Nightingale Memorial at the Royal United Service Institution, London, undated, (1 photograph of a sculpture) 5 x 6 inches (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Florence Nightingale Memorial in the Cloister of Santa Croce, Florence, undated, (1 photograph of a sculpture) 10 x 7.5 inches (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Florence Nightingale Memorial Royal Military Hospital, Millbrook, Cornwall, undated, (1 photograph) 8 x 6 inches (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - The Generals and Staff at Sebastopol, undated, (1 photograph of a drawing) 4 x 7.75 inches (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Reproduction of the original image by Barlser. Includes one photographic reproduction in folder 3.
  - Florence Nightingale Memorial, Royal Military Hospital, Millbank, London, undated, (1 photograph of a print) 8 x 6 inches (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - The Florence Nightingale Statue, Waterloo Place, London, undated, (1 photograph) 8 x 6 inches (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Lea Hurst, Miss Nightingale's Home, undated, (1 engraving) 8 x 6 inches (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Miss Florence Nightingale and her Nurses in the East, undated, (1 photograph) 4.5 x 6.25 inches (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Miss Nightingale in the Hospital at Scutari, undated, (1 engraving) 9 x 11.5 inches (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Includes one reproduction in photographic format.
  - Miss Nightingale 'When Pain and Anguish Wring the Brow...', undated, (1 engraving) 13.75 x 10.5 inches (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - The Nightingale Corner in the Johns Hopkins Hospital School of Nurses, Nurses Home, Baltimore, Maryland, undated, (1 photograph) 4.5 x 6.25 inches (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Depicts the Nightingale Chair with a small statue and various portraits of Florence Nightingale.
  - Portrait of an anonymous man, undated, (1 photograph) 4.5 x 6.25 inches (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Anonymous seated man reading a book in a study or library. Signed by Reginald Hamish, possibly.
  - Portrait of Florence Nightingale, half-length, with a facsimile of her signature, "Yours very truly, Florence Nightingale, undated", (1 stipple-engraving) 7.75 x 5.5 inches (Box 3, Folder 8)
    London, George Routledge and Company.
  - Portrait of Florence Nightingale, seated in an arm chair with papers in her hands, undated, (1 photograph) 9.5 x 7.5 inches (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Includes one duplicate in photographic format.
  - Portrait of Florence Nightingale, three-quarters-length, standing, with a facsimile of her signature, undated, (1 steel-engraving) 9.75 x 6.75 inches (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Engraved by J. Cole.
  - St. Thomas Hospital, Southwark, London, undated, (1 photograph) 5.5 x 8 inches (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Statue erected circa 1870.
  - Statue of Florence Nightingale as the "Lady with the Lamp, undated", (1 photograph of an engraving of the statue) 4 x 2.75 inches (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Statue located at the Florence Nightingale Home at St. Thomas' Hospital, London. Engraving drawn by H. Bonham Carter and engraved by C. H. Jeens.
  - Statue of Florence Nightingale unveiled by the Duke of Devonshire at Derby, undated, (1 photograph of a statue) 8.5 x 6.5 inches (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Sculpted by Countess Feodora Gleichen.
- Other Materials, undated
  Contains undated manuscripts regarding accounts from the Crimean War, a postcard of Florence Nightingale's birth and death place, and the original folio binder in which the Nightingale Photographs and Prints were housed.
  - The Early Home and Last Resting Place of Florence Nightingale, (1 postcard) (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Hospital and Cemetery at Scutari (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Undated, double-sided typescript containing a description of the hospital and cemetery at Scutari. Includes a two-page facsimile of the manuscript.
  - A Ward in the Hospital at Scutari (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Undated, double-sided typescript describing the hospital at Scutari. Includes a two-page facsimile of the manuscript.
  - Original large-format black folio that contained Howard Kelly's collection of Nightingale images.